בוקר טוב *Boker Tov*, today’s דף daf, *Daf* is ס"ו *Samech-Vav*, 66,
and we pick up at the bottom of ס"ה עמוד ב' *Samech-Hey
Amud Beis*, and we are dealing with the differences about a bird
חטאת chattas *Chatas* and a bird עולה olah, *Olah*, and there’s an
interesting debate because the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is very much reflecting the
פסוקים pesukim *Pesukim*. So the bird עולה olah *Olah*, right, by the
bird חטאת chattas *Chatas* it says לא יבדיל lo yavdil? *Lo Yavdil*,
you don’t sever the head. Here, this will be the head, I
guess. That’s my picture of a bird. Anyway, so you use the
fingernail and you don’t sever it, but not only does it mean
you don’t cut all the way through, it means you only cut
one of the סימנים simanim, *Simanim*, either the trachea or the esophagus,
and they understand that by the עולה olah *Olah* you do fully
separate it and the head off. So that’s one major difference besides
the location of where they’re done. And the other major difference is
what you do with the blood. Here it says והזה *V’hizah*, that
first you squirt the blood, you know, I guess you hold the
body and the blood squirts, and then you squeeze out the remainder,
והנשאר ימצה אל יסוד המזבח *V’hanishar yimatzei el yesod hamizbe’ach*. And here
it doesn’t say והזה *V’hizah* by the עולה olah. *Olah*, it just
says ונמצה דמו venimtzah damo *V’nimtza damo*, so there’s just the squeezing
out. So those are the differences, and one of the interesting things
that the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* was just debating or discussing was the
position of רבי אליעזר ברבי שמעון Rabbi Eliezer be-Rabbi Shimon? *Rabbi Eliezer
bar Rabbi Shimon*, who said that if you do the חטאת chattas
*Chatas* like the עולה olah, *Olah*, if you sever both סימנים simanim.
*Simanim*, it actually is going to be כשר kosher *Kasher*. Okay, which
is interesting. Now you could have said, what do you mean, the
פסוק pasuk. *Pasuk* says לא יבדיל lo yavdil *Lo Yavdil*, so maybe
just the very violation of that verse should make it invalid, but
that’s not what the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* focused on. The גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* focused on the question about if you severed both, have you
made it like an עולה olah. *Olah*? And it's somehow doing it
like an עולה olah *Olah* that invalidates it. So the point is,
and now why would you not do it like an... well, it
does seem that you're doing it like an עולה olah *Olah*, but
then it got into these questions of well, maybe not, because since
there’s a הלכה halacha? *Halacha* that as you’re cutting the first סימן
siman *Siman* you have to cut most of the flesh, by the
time you get to the second סימן siman. *Siman*, there will have
been a שהייה shehiyah, *Shehiya*, a pause between the two, would that
have invalidated by the עולה olah *Olah* if you paused between the
first or the second סימן siman *Siman* and so on? So it
got to a series of questions of if you did this and
you cut both סימנים simanim *Simanim*, would that have been something comparable
to that would have been כשר kosher. *Kasher* by an עולה olah
*Olah*? Okay, and that was the whole discussion we had yesterday. So
now we pick up at the bottom of ס"ה עמוד ב' *Samech-Hey
Amud Beis*, and it says like this:
מכלל *Michlal*. So there’s a little ב *Beis* at the beginning in
parentheses at the beginning of a line about ten lines from the
bottom and it’s two words before that. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* says מכלל דבעינן דרוב בשר בתחילה *Michlal de-ba’inan de-rov basar bit’chilah*.
Since you said the question here was since after you cut סימן
siman *Siman* one, you cut through to get to סימן siman, *Siman*
one, you cut a minority of the flesh of the neck, you
cut סימן siman *Siman* one, and then you cut the remainder
of the majority of the flesh, and then the question was if
you moved on to סימן siman *Siman* two, would that make it
like an עולה olah *Olah* because would that be something that would
the pausing between סימן siman, *Siman* one and סימן siman, *Siman* two
make it invalid had it been an עולה olah *Olah*? But what
we infer from that is that you’re required to cut the majority
of the flesh of the neck as you’re cutting through and that’s
what the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* is now going to explore. מכלל דבעינן
רוב בשר rov basar בתחילה *Michlal de-ba’inan rov basar bit’chilah*. Do you
tell me לכתחילה *L’chatchila* it’s clear you need to cut through the
majority of the flesh of the neck by the חטאת chatat. *Chatas*?
So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says אין In, *In*, yes, ותניא *v’tanya*,
we taught like this in a ברייתא *Baraisa*. כיצד מולקין חטאת העוף
Chatas ha-of, *Keitzad molkin chatas ha-of*? How do you do the מליקה
melikah, *Melika*? חותך שדרה ומפרקת *Chotech shedrah u-mifrekes*? You cut through the
spinal cord and the back bone or the neck bone, I guess,
בלא רוב בשר *belo rov basar*, and as you’re getting to סימן
siman *Siman* one you do not cut away the majority of the
flesh because were you to cut away the majority of the
flesh then before you would get to שחיטה shechitah? *Shechitah*, I mean
this is מליקה melikah, *Melika*, it’s not שחיטה shechitah. *Shechitah*, but right,
if you cut away the majority of the flesh, then before you
actually sever the סימן siman *Siman* which is the כשר kosher *Kasher*
act, it would already be considered like essentially dead. So therefore you
have not to do the majority of the flesh of the neck
עד שיגיע לושט או לקנה *ad she-yagia la-veshet o la-kaneh*, until you
get either to the ושט *veshet* or the קנה *kaneh*. I think
that’s the esophagus or the trachea. הגיע לושט או לקנה *Higia la-veshet
o la-kaneh*, if you get to the ושט *veshet* or the קנה
*kaneh*, חותך סימן siman אחד *chotech siman echad*, you cut one of
them, או רובו *o rubo*, or the majority of one, you don’t
have to cut it fully, ורוב בשר עמו *v’rov basar imo*, and
in that act of cutting סימן siman *Siman* one, you finish cutting
enough of the flesh of the neck that now you’ve cut through
the majority of the flesh. But you don’t cut it all off
because that’s לא יבדיל lo yavdil, *Lo Yavdil*. ובעולה שנים או רוב
שנים *U-v’olah shnayim o rov shnayim*, and when you’re dealing with an
עולה olah *Olah* you have to cut both of the סימנים simanim.
*Simanim* or the majority of both. Okay. By the עולה olah *Olah*
do you do the second סימן siman *Siman* after רוב בשר *rov
basar*? No, you do it before. And that was the question, which
is so if you were doing this and then after רוב בשר
*rov basar* you continue to the second סימן siman. *Siman*, so by
an עולה olah *Olah* you’ve cut two without doing רוב בשר *rov
basar* because again the point is you can’t basically kill the animal
before you do the ritual killing of it, before you do the
מליקה melikah *Melika*. So you have to wait for the רוב בשר
*rov basar* till after you cut the necessary סימנים simanim, *Simanim*. So
that would be the question about what would. be by an עולה
olah, if you actually did רוב בשר between סימן siman? two. And
that's שהייה, shehiyah, it's actually interesting, in addition to שהייה, the גמרא
Gemara, could have asked it, you know, you've already killed it in
another way. And that raised the fascinating conceptual question, which is normally
when we שחט shecht birds just for meat, you know, normally, you
only require one סימן. siman When the תורה Torah requires the second
סימן siman by an עולה, olah is it redefining the act of
שחיטה? shechitah I mean it's already redefining because it's מליקה, melikah it's
not שחיטה. shechita But is it redefining it that saying like it's
not like you made it, you know, כשר kosher meat, you're not
like until you cut both or is it saying no, by cutting
סימן siman... one, you've done the act of מליקה, melikah then there's
another requirement that you finish and you sever it completely. And that
was exactly the conceptual question that we dealt with yesterday. Okay, so
now the גמרא Gemara says like this. אמרו קמיה דרבי ירמיה. Amru
kamei de-Rabbi Yirmiyah. So they said this whole discussion to רבי ירמיה
Rabbi Yirmiyah and he said to them the following. So this debate
about what is the reason of רבי אלעזר בן שמעון Rabbi Elazar
ben Shimon why he says that if you actually severed both by
a חטאת chatat. it would still be כשר. kosher. So אמר לא
שמיע להו הא דאמר רבי שמעון בן לקיש משום רבי אלעזר בן
דסא משום רבי אלעזר בן שמוע. amar lo shemi'a lehu ha d'amar
Rabbi Shimon ben Lakish mishum Rabbi Elazar ben Das mishum Rabbi Elazar
ben Shamuah. So didn't they hear this whole tradition of, it's interesting,
of two רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazars about what רבי אלעזר בן שמעון
Rabbi Elazar ben Shimon's position was? אמר האי רבי אלעזר בן שמעון,
Amar hai Rabbi Elazar ben Shimon, that the explanation of רבי אלעזר
בן שמעון Rabbi Elazar ben Shimon of why it is כשר kosher
if you continue to sever the second סימן, siman, so until now
the גמרא Gemara. has essentially said it's כשר kosher. because it would
not have been a valid way of doing an עולת העוף. olat
ha-of. And therefore what invalidates cutting off the second סימן siman, is
you're treating the חטאת chatat like an עולה olah, and רבי אלעזר
בן שמעון Rabbi Elazar ben Shimon says no, that wouldn't have been
valid by an עולה olah so you didn't treat the חטאת chatat
like an עולה. olah, That's how we conceptualized the debate yesterday. So
here, רבי, Rabbi, who is it who's saying this? Here, רבי ירמיה
Rabbi Yirmiyah is saying wait, wait, wait. There's a different explanation for
רבי אלעזר בן שמעון Rabbi Elazar ben Shimon why he's saying it's
כשר. kasher, Not because oh, you didn't do it like an עולה,
olah, this wouldn't have been כשר kosher like an עולה. olah That's
not the point. Here's why he's saying it's כשר. kosher, He says,
אמר האי רבי אלעזר בן שמעון שמעתי בחטאות שמבדילין. amar hai Rabbi
Elazar ben Shimon shamati be-chattasot she-mavdilin. I heard that it's okay to
sever it. ומאי לא יבדיל? U-mai lo yavdil? You've misunderstood the פסוק.
pasuk The פסוק pasuk? when it says don't sever means אין צריך
להבדיל, ein tzarich le-havdil, it's not required. Okay? You know, you have
a lot of פסוקים like that. לא תרצח, Lo tirzach, לא תנאף.
lo tinaph. Okay, I'm just kidding. Anyway. So, so but in this
context obviously it does make sense, okay? Which was first in the
פסוק? pasuk The עולה olah, is first. But the עולה olah. never
says יבדיל. yavdil. Right, the עולה olah we're just somehow inferring that
the עולה olah, you sever, okay? But okay, he's reading ולא יבדיל,
velo yavdil, you can as long as you basically fundamentally do מליקה
Melika without even having to be מבדיל. mavdil. That's your second דרשה,
drasha, then you can say ולא יבדיל velo yavdil makes sense, you
don't have to do it by the עולה Olah. since the עולה
Olah? was already mentioned. Exactly. And since עולה Olah, is mentioned first...
Right. So, oh, so if you, right, if since עולה Olah is
mentioned first... Except the דרשה drasha that we've implicitly that you are
being מבדיל mavdil there, so then this is saying this you don't
have to, exactly. And once the תורה Torah is saying you don't
have to, it's implicitly saying it's okay if you do, okay? אמר
ליה רב אחאי בריה דרבא לרב אשי. Amar leih Rav Achei berei
de-Rava le-Rav Ashi. So רב אחאי Rav Achei the son of רבא
Rava said to רב אשי, Rav Ashi, אלא מעתה גבי בור דכתיב,
ella mei-ata gabei bor de-chtiv, so I asked my question about לא
תרצח, lo tirzach, לא תנאף, lo tinaph, the גמרא Gemara, is going
to ask a similar question. ולא יכסנו. Velo yechasenu. It says if
a person digs a well and doesn't cover it and then some
an animal falls in he has to pay. הכא נמי דאין צריך
לכסות? Hacha nami dein tzarich le-chasot? If you dig a well and
you know you don't have to cover it, okay? So that's, so
the גמרא Gemara asks הכי השתא? hachi hashta? How could you read
it that way? התם כיון דכתיב בעל הבור ישלם, Hasham kivan de-chtiv
ba'al ha-bor yeshalem, that the owner of the pit has to pay,
עילויה הוא דרמי לכסויי, ilu yehu de-ramei le-chasuyei, clearly you're paying because
you didn't cover it. So context makes it clear that the absence
of covering it is a cause of
liability. אבל הכא, Aval hacha, here, מכדי כתיב והקריבו. michti ktiv ve-hikrivo.
Now we're going to get to the question about how do we
assume by an עולה Olah you have to separate it? Because by
yesterday, because we said, right here it says you should bring it
to the כהן kohen to the מזבח, mizbe'ach, actually part of the
reason we know that you sever it, right, is that it says
והקטיר ve-hiktir twice, offer to the מזבח mizbe'ach and offer it, so
that's understanding that you actually have two parts, a head and a
neck. But that doesn't actually prove that in the act of מליקה
Melika you sever it. You could do מליקה melikah, one way and
then you know continue and then chop it off afterwards, okay? But
somehow והקריבו אל הכהן, ve-hikrivo el ha-kohen, you bring it, I'm not,
you know, some, I mean, let's look at רש"י, Rashi, רש"י Rashi
explains this דרשה, drasha, I really,
רש"י Rashi says one minute, where's רש"י? Rashi? רש"י Rashi says what,
one minute, where's רש"י? Rashi? Is it the line... Yeah,
okay, מכדי כתיב, michti ktiv, yeah, first line. בעולת העוף והקריבו. Be-olat
ha-of ve-hikrivo. ומנא לן לרבי אלעזר בן שמעון הבדלה בעולת העוף בכל
שוחטין. U-minei naflan le-Rabbi Elazar ben Shimon havdalah be-olat ha-of be-chol shochtin.
Okay, ולא דרשינן מלק והקטיר קדשי המזבח velo darshinan malak ve-hiktir kadshei
ha-mizbe'ach etc. etc.
So somehow רש"י Rashi doesn't even spell it out here, you have
to go look at that גמרא. Gemara, No, that's like, it's like
four lines down in... Oh, four lines he says it? והקריבו דמשמע
חלק זה מן החטאת. Ve-hikrivo de-mashma chilek zeh min ha-chattat. Oh right.
So somehow והקריבו... ve-hikrivo...
Oh right, so somehow והקריבו, vehikrivo, you're right, it's the opposite. This
one you do somehow different than the way that one, of course
that begs the question, right? Is this saying—anyway, we'll take a look.
So that's the point, והקריבו vehikrivo was saying that this is distinct
from that, from however you do the שחיטה shechita here, and this
is going to be distinct. So let's see how the גמרא Gemara.
plays it out. So when it says like לא יחצנו lo yechatzenu
in general, לא lo means don't or you didn't or whatever. How
come here we're reading it to say you don't have to? So
it says like this: התם, hatam, so—but הכא, hacha, מכדי כתיב והקריבו.
michdi ksiv vehikrivo. You do this one, the עולה, Olah, different than
the
חטאת. chatat, חילק הכתוב בין חטאת העוף לעולת העוף. hilek hakatuv bein
chatat ha'of l'olat ha'of. It's telling you: do the עולה Olah, in
a different way than the חטאת. chatat לא יבדיל למה לי? lo
yavdil lama li? So what is לא lo, יבדיל? Now, לא יבדיל
למה לי lo yavdil lama li is a strange פסוק—I mean, it's
a strange statement. Why do you need to say it? You need
to say it to tell me either you don't have to or
you're not required. But basically the way רש״י—רש״י has a couple ways
of reading this גמרא, Gemara okay, none of which are fully satisfying,
but his basic point is, is that if you're distinguishing these two,
right, what allows you to read it in a way that goes
to sort of opposite, you know, diametrically opposite? You know, you either—you
either read this to say you have to divide it into two,
you have to cut two, and then you should read this to
say you don't have to. Or if you read this to say
you're not allowed to divide into two, then you should read this
to say you're allowed to divide. Since it doesn't explicitly say what
you do by the עולה, Olah, it's sort of like תפסת מרובה
לא תפסת. tafasta merubeh lo tafasta. You can only move—distinguish it one
stage, you're not entitled to say it's completely the opposite. So if
we're going to work with an assumption that the עולה Olah has
to both be severed, then therefore the only way we could get
to that is reading לא Lo, יבדיל as you don't have to
sever. If this is you don't have to sever, then this is
you have to sever. And we know that's true by an עולה,
Olah, that you have to sever. But if we're going to read
this to say that לא יבדיל, which is you're not allowed to,
that would not get us to where we needed to get by
an עולה, Olah, because then we'd only be entitled to say by
an עולה Olah you're allowed to sever, but not that you have
to. Okay. אלא לא יבדיל למה לי שמע מינה אין צריך להבדיל.
ella lo yavdil lama li shma mina ein tzarich lehavdil. Okay. So
anyway,
that's the way he reads it. So that's why it's כשר, kosher
not because technically that thing would have been—would have been פסול pasul
by an עולה, Olah but just the way he reads the verse,
that the verse is giving you the option of severing it or
not severing it. Last line here about the עולה. Olah מיצה דם
הגוף, mitzah dam haguf, you squeeze out the blood of the body
against the wall, you squeeze out the blood of the head, and
then the משנה mishnah says that if you actually—the one thing that's
critical is the—is the blood of the body. The blood of the
head is not מעכב. me'akev. So we want to know where you
get that from, because there's only one ונמצה דמו ve-nimtzah damo. here.
Okay. So the גמרא Gemara, says: תנו רבנן: tanu rabanan: עולה אף
על פי שמיצה דם גוף ולא מיצה דם הראש. olah af al
pi shemitzah dam guf v'lo mitzah dam harosh. It's valid even if
you squeezed out just the blood of the body, not the blood
of the head. יכול מיצה דם הראש ולא מיצה דם הגוף? yachol
mitzah dam harosh v'lo mitzah dam haguf? Maybe—maybe it should be the
head that's more important? תלמוד לומר הוא. talmud lomar hu. It says
עולה הוא, olah hu, אשה ריח ניחוח, isheh reiach nichoach, or somewhere
it says עולה הוא. olah hu. Anyway, okay. הוא. hu. So it,
it meaning that there—somehow only one of them is necessary. מאי תלמודא?
mai talmuda? Where do you get it from? אמר רבינא: amar Ravina:
מסתברא דרוב דמים בגוף שכיחי. mistavra derov damim beguf shechichi. Okay. So
this is a very logical position. If one of those things is
going to be critical, so most of the blood is in the
body and not in the head, so we're just going to assume
that's the one that the תורה Torah is insisting on. Okay. הדרן
עלך חטאת העוף. hadran alach chatat ha'of. So that is now the
end of that. Ironically, you know, you'd have thought, okay, we introduced
birds, we haven't really been dealing with birds at all. If it's
going to interrupt it here, maybe we're done with birds. Very—sometimes it's
very strange the way a פרק perek seems to end right in
the middle of a discussion and then continue on to the next
פרק. perek. Okay. So we actually here—the next משנה mishnah is exactly
the discussion, like it—it's like literally connected to the previous משנה, mishnah,
so I can't explain why it's a new פרק, perek, but let's
take a look. And this exactly ties into what we were discussing
at the end of yesterday, beginning of today about the question about:
are you doing an עולה Olah. like a חטאת Chatat or a
חטאת Chatat. like an עולה, Olah that doing it in the way
of the other an—of the other one would be a source of
invalidating it. Who divided the משנה mishnah into פרקים? prakim? Who did?
It's assumed רבי Rebbi did. The individual
משניות—not mishnayot so. I don't know exactly when we assume those were
divided. There's often also a different division in the actual, like, you
know, משניות mishnayot manuscripts than there are in the גמרא. Gemara. The
גמרא, Gemara you know—but the גמרא Gemara itself, you should know, when
you have a משנה mishnah that appears in a block in the
גמרא, Gemara that was actually not—that was a printer, that was not
actually the גמרא. Gemara The גמרא Gemara you just had the text
of the גמרא, Gemara and then the printer came in and he
decided like which part of the משנה mishnah to sort of, you
know, put up there and then chop it up and then which
part to put next. So—but yes, but the dividing into the individual
משניות mishnayot is post-רבי, Rebbi, it might even be גאוניק Geonic or
something, I don't know exactly the date. But the פרקים prakim is
רבי, Rebbi, is—you know, at that period.
Okay. חטאת העוף שעשאה למטה כמעשה חטאת. chatat ha'of she'asasah lematah k'ma'aseh
chatat. So the חטאת, Chatat, the bird—remember the birds and the animals
are reversed. So the animal חטאת Chatat, is the top, because you'd
use the finger with the horns.
This evokes what we just got discussed, what we were just discussing.
You do the חטאת Chatat like an עולה. Olah, What does it
mean to do it like an עולה? Olah. It could mean you
do it up at the top, but here it sounds like you're
doing it at the bottom. So there's two fundamental differences. One is
you could sever both סימנים, simanim, that's what we were talking about,
or it could mean that rather than squirting the blood, you just
squeeze it out. Alright, so anyway we'll see that in the גמרא.
Gemara But if you did it like an עולה, Olah לשם חטאת,
leshem Chatat, even if it's לשם חטאת, leshem Chatat, doesn't matter. The
doing the עבודה avodah like an עולה Olah invalidates. If you did
it כמעשה עולה לשם עולה, kemaaseh Olah leshem Olah, or you did
it like an עולה Olah, and you had intent like an עולה,
Olah don't think oh, now I'll redefine it. Sorry, you don't get
to redefine it. It's a חטאת. Chatat, פסולה, Psula, either way it's
invalid.
עשה למעלה כמעשה כולן, asah lemala k'maaseh kulan, if you did it
at the top half of the altar, whether you did it with
intent to be a חטאת, Chatat whether you did it with intent
to be an עולה, Olah, פסולה, Psula, it's invalid. Cause you know,
and that's, there are two הוה אמינא havaminas you could have said.
You could have said if I do it exactly right as a
חטאת, Chatat, לשם חטאת, leshem Chatat, maybe doing it in a slightly
wrong place won't invalidate. So you have to say no, that invalidates.
Or you could say if I do it at the top half,
which is the place of the עולה, Olah. and I do it
for sake of the עולה Olah and I do it like an
עולה, Olah. maybe that'll redefine it, you know, walks like a duck
and quacks like a duck, right? No, it doesn't matter. So if
you do it at the top half, you can't make it into
an עולה, Olah? and as a חטאת Chatat it's invalid. So either
way it's invalid. So you gotta do everything right in order for
it to be valid. Similarly,
עולת העוף שעשאה למעלה כמעשה עולה לשם עולה כשרה. Olat HaOf she-asah
lemala kemaaseh Olah leshem Olah keshera. An עולת העוף Olat HaOf you
did it above, you did it the right way, you did it
with the right intent, כשרה, keshera, you got all three variables. However,
any other variable you're going to play with is going to invalidate
it. כמעשה עולה לשם חטאת, kemaaseh Olah leshem Chatat, if you had...
actually I shouldn't say invalidate it'll be a problem, because here there's
a difference. If you do it שלא לשמה shelo lishmo of a
חטאת, Chatat, so any animal that's not a חטאת Chatat, that you
do שלא לשמה, shelo lishmo, what's the
הלכה? halacha כשרה ובלבד שלא עלה לבעליה. keshera u'velvad shelo ala l'ba'aleha.
That actually the animal is כשרה, keshera, you can burn it on
the altar, but the owners don't get credit. So that's the difference
of the שלא לשמה. shelo lishmo. כמעשה חטאת לשם עולה, kemaaseh Chatat
leshem Olah, however if you did the עולה Olah, like a חטאת,
Chatat, now this is more obviously invalid because an עולה Olah? like
a חטאת Chatat, minimum could mean the easy obvious thing it means
is you only severed one סימן siman and not two סימנים. simanim.
Okay, so you didn't do the right שחיטה shechita. essentially. So that's
going to be invalid. Or כמעשה חטאת לשם חטאת. kemaaseh Chatat leshem
Chatat. Let's say you tried to do it all like a חטאת,
Chatat you had in mind a חטאת, Chatat, you only did one
סימן, siman פסולה, Psula, those cases it's invalid. Why is that case
פסולה? Psula? An עולה Olah, could be done שלא לשמה. shelo lishmo.
Oh right, so you're right, but because the מעשה חטאת, maaseh Chatat,
if the מעשה חטאת maaseh Chatat means one סימן, siman, so then
it's because you didn't do the proper שחיטה of the עולה. Olah.
So כמעשה חטאת לשם חטאת... kemaaseh Chatat leshem Chatat... what does it
mean to do an עולה Olah. שלא לשמה shelo lishmo let's say
by סתם? stam? You have intent that you... but you do it
the right way for an עולה, Olah it has to still be
for the right way for an עולה. Olah, Right, I actually sever
both סימנים simanim. but I think it's a חטאת, Chatat, or I
know it's an עולה Olah. but I want it to be a
חטאת, Chatat. then it'll be כשרה ולא עלה לבעלים. keshera velo ala
l'baalim. But if I only do one סימן siman then it's not
the שלא לשמה shelo lishmo which is the issue, the problem is
I didn't do the מליקה melikah correctly. Okay, so the bigger חידוש
chiddush is remember is the reverse, is if you do the חטאת
Chatas, and you sever both סימנים. Simanim. Why does doing an extra
סימן Siman. invalidate? That's what we just got through discussing, the ולא
יבדיל. ve-lo yavdil. But doing one less סימן Siman. by an עולה
Olah is that clearly will invalidate. Okay, so עשה למטה כמעשה כולן
פסולה. asah lemata kemaaseh kulan Psula. And here's the same point, if
you do it below, then there's two points, you might have thought
okay look, I did it לשם עולה, leshem Olah, I did it
the way of an עולה, Olah, maybe doing it in the slightly
wrong place doesn't invalidate. No, it does. Or you might have thought
if I did it below and I did it for the sake
of a חטאת, Chatas, like a חטאת, Chatas maybe I get to
redefine it as a חטאת. Chatas. So the answer is no, that's
also no good. Okay, so there if you do it in the
wrong place regardless what you had in mind and how you did
it, it's invalid. If you do an עולת העוף Olat HaOf standing
on the floor of the עזרה Azara instead of on the סובב?
Sovev? Right. And you actually sort of squirted it, you managed to
get it squirted there? Yeah, so I think we say that the
הלכה is, the גמרא Gemara is about to get to it, that
the מליקה melikah can be anywhere, from remembering correctly, it's just that
the actual like מיצוי הדם mitzui hadam has to be... oh no,
but wait, I'm trying to see if I remember this correctly, because...
yes, but because an עולה Olah, requires מיצוי, mitzui, מיצוי הדם, mitzui
hadam, and not הזאה, haza'ah, you have to... I mean if you're
very tall I guess you'd be able to do the מיצוי mitzui
standing on the floor. Okay, but yes, in theory. I think. Alright,
so now the גמרא Gemara says like this: דשאני במאי? De-shani be-mai?
So now this thing that you did, a חטאת, Chatas an עולה,
Olah, how did we start? We started with a חטאת, Chatas a
חטאת Chatas like an עולה. Olah, So I said that meant that
you severed both סימנים, Simanim. that was actually the debate of רבי
אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer and רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, is doing an extra
סימן invalidate? Okay? כמעשה עולה לשם חטאת? Ke-ma'aseh Olah shem Chatas? כמעשה
עולה? Ke-ma'aseh Olah? כמעשה Ke-ma'aseh לשם חטאת? leshem Chatas? No, you're doing
an עולה Olah, like the מעשה עולה. ma'aseh Olah. We're still dealing
with the bird as a חטאת. Chatas, Okay? You're doing a חטאת
Chatas like an עולה. Olah What does it mean to do it
like an עולה? Olah, So again, the thing that you immediately think
of, or I immediately think of, is the one סימן versus two
סימנים, Simanim but that was, that means that you're going to do
an extra סימן. Will that invalidate? That was the debate we just
got through. Okay? דשאני במאי? De-shani be-mai? This חטאת Chatas, that you
did like an עולה, Olah what did you do? How did you
change it and make it like an עולה? Olah אילימא דשאני במליקה,
Ileima de-shani bi-melikah, the מליקה, melikah. that you severed a second
סימן? נימא דלא כרבי אליעזר ברבי שמעון, Neima delo ke-Rabbi Eliezer be-Rabbi
Shimon, so should we assume our משנה Mishnah is against רבי אליעזר
ברבי שמעון? Rabbi Eliezer be-Rabbi Shimon. Which is, okay, why not? But
the point is, we'd rather not have it be part of a
debate. This is exactly what we were debating yesterday and the beginning
of today. דאמר שמעתי שמבדילין בחטאת העוף. De-amar shamati she-mavdilin be-Chatas ha-of.
He says, yeah, that you can. So should we say our משנה
Mishnah is not like him? And that if you sever the second
סימן you invalidate? So the גמרא Gemara. says: why not? ולא אוקימנא
דלא כרבי אליעזר ברבי שמעון? Ve-lo ukimna delo ke-Rabbi Eliezer be-Rabbi Shimon?
Okay, but we just got through saying that, you know, yesterday, that
our משנה Mishnah wasn't רבי אליעזר ברבי שמעון. Rabbi Eliezer be-Rabbi Shimon.
So that's not a problem. Fine, it's debated. But our משנה Mishnah
takes this side of the debate, that if you sever the second
סימן by a חטאת Chatas העוף, Ha'of you invalidate it. Okay, so
that's one read, that we're talking about מליקה melikah. and it's part
of this debate and it's invalid, not like רבי Rabbi אליעזר Eliezer
ברבי שמעון. The גמרא Gemara says: לא, now you don't have to
say that. There's another way you can read it that's not even
debated. דשאני בהזאה, De-shani be-haza'ah, that you did the הזאה haza'ah differently.
Remember, those are the two major points. This says והזה מדמו ve-hizah
midamo and this just says ונמצה דמו. So here you have your
חטאת Chatas and rather than just squirting immediately after you severed it,
you squeezed it out against the wall. You never did the הזאה.
haza'ah. Okay? Now that should obviously be an invalid because anything of
the blood that you do wrong, if you're not doing the blood
the right way, you invalidate. Okay? So that's why you invalidate when
you do the blood the wrong way. דשאני בהזאה. De-shani be-haza'ah. הכי
נמי מסתברא. Hakhi nami mistabra. You know, that makes sense, that we're
talking about not the מליקה melikah but the blood. מדקתני סיפא: Midikataney
seifa: עשאה למעלה כמעשה כולם פסולה. asahlah le-ma'alah ke-ma'aseh khulam pesulah. Because
the end says by the חטאת, chatat if you did it above,
like either fully like a חטאת chatat, or fully like an עולה,
Olah. it doesn't matter, you're doing it above, it's invalid. Okay, so
what does
it
mean? What's the 'it'? You did 'it' above. And doing 'it' above
invalidates. So when I said it, I said: where did the blood
go? Did it go to the top half of the altar, the
bottom half of the altar? Right? That's, okay, so that's the point
the גמרא Gemara is going to make. The 'it' could not mean
the מליקה. melikah So no, clearly when it says if at top
half it's bad, we're talking about where you put the blood, where
the blood squirted, not where you did the
מליקה. melikah דשאני במאי? De-shani be-mai? What's the 'it' that you're doing
above? אילימא דשאני במליקה, Ileima de-shani bi-melikah, you did the מליקה melikah
above? האמר מר מליקה בכל מקום במזבח כשרה. Ha-amar mar melikah be-khol
makom bamizbe'ach kesherah. Right, this is sort of what Yitzchak was asking
about the flip case, about the עולה. Olah So we actually say
that wherever you do the מליקה melikah it's okay. The תורה Torah
cares not where the מליקה melikah. is done while, I mean, it
cares where, or certainly if you did it in the environs of
the מזבח mizbe'ach it's kosher. It cares where the blood is put.
אלא לאו דשאני בהזאה. Ela lav de-shani be-haza'ah. So when the end
talks about if you did the thing, the חטאת, chatat which goes
below, you did it above, it's invalid, the doing 'it' above there
clearly means the blood hitting the altar. So since that's the focus
of the doing 'it' above, that's also the focus of when you
did it like an עולה. Olah Doing a חטאת chatat, like an
עולה Olah doesn't mean you did the מליקה melikah, like an עולה,
Olah it means you treated the blood like an עולה. Olah, So
rather than squirting the blood, you actually just directly squeezed the blood.
ומדסיפא בהזאה רישא נמי בהזאה? U-midei seifa be-haza'ah, reisha nami be-haza'ah? Since
in the end when it's talking about the wrong location it's talking
about where the blood was
squirted, the beginning also where it's talking about you did it like
an עולה Olah doesn't mean you did the מליקה melikah, like an
עולה, Olah it means you did the blood like an עולה, Olah
rather than squirting it you squeezed it. So the גמרא Gemara says:
מי דאיריא? mi-de'irya? What, you think that's a proof? הא כדאיתא והא
כדאיתא. Ha-kedisa ve-ha-kedisa. Everyone is what it means in its context. So
obviously you're right, the doing 'it' in the wrong place means the
squirting of the blood, but when it says you changed it and
you made it like an עולה, Olah that doesn't have to be
talking about the blood, that could be talking about the מליקה. melikah,
So it's, the read is at least it's nicer, but it certainly
doesn't prove that that's the meaning of the משנה. Mishnah. So there's
two possibilities of what it means when you do a חטאת chatat
like an עולה, Olah, you invalidate it. One is you didn't do
the blood properly. Then it's obvious, then what invalidates it is not
the fact that it was done like an עולה, Olah. what invalidates
is you didn't do what you needed to do, you didn't squirt
the blood, you squeezed it out. The חידוש chiddush is if it
means the מליקה, melikah that somehow even though I did everything I
was supposed to do, I slaughtered the סימן... I did the blood
properly, whatever, because I did it in a way that would have
been כשר kosher, by an עולה Olah somehow that invalidates. And the
גמרא Gemara never gives a verse, you know, never gives a basis
for that. Again, you could hinge it on the ולא יבדיל v'lo
yavdil and say if you violated what the תורה Torah explicitly says
don't do this, that violation invalidates, but the גמרא Gemara never spells
out how we know it invalidates. That's why there's this huge תוספות
Tosafot in the previous דף, right? Because he's trying to figure out,
like normally you need the verse to repeat something to know that
it invalidates, and here the גמרא Gemara never deals with like how
we know, you know, that a variation will פסול, passul, will invalidate.
Okay, so it doesn't really get fully explained in our גמרא. Gemara
All right, so that's the חטאת chatat, that you did like an
עולה, Ola and similarly if you do an עולה Ola? like a
חטאת, chatat, so you invalidate. So דשני במה, deshani be'mai, in what
way did you make an עולה Ola? like a חטאת chatat that
invalidates it? So the easiest thing here to say is the מליקה,
melikah you only severed one סימן, and because you only severed one
סימן, the reason it's invalid is not because it's like a חטאת,
chatat, but just you didn't do what you needed to do, you
didn't sever both
סימנים. Simanim. דשני במה, deshani be'mai, what did you vary?
אילמא דשני במליקה, eilema deshani be'melikah, that what you varied was the
מליקה, melikah that you only did one סימן this עולה. Ola מכדי
תני סיפא כולן אין מטמאין בבית הבליעה, midei t'ni seifa kulan ein
metamin be'veit habli'ah, we're getting to the end, which is the משנה
Mishna we're about to read, and the next משנה Mishna is going
to say that here you basically did this improperly, you did a
חטאת chatat like an עולה Ola and an עולה Ola, like a
חטאת, chatat and nevertheless we don't treat it like a נבלה. neveilah.
All right, so because a נבלה, neveilah, what's meaning here something that
if it were not a קרבן korban would be a נבלה neveilah
because you severed it from the back of the head, you didn't
do a proper שחיטה. Okay, and you might think that therefore as
soon as it becomes invalid as a קרבן, korban, we now look
at it as it wasn't שחט, shachtet, it was basically chopped off
the back of the head and it's a נבלה. neveilah. And the
חידוש chiddush of the next משנה Mishna is that it's not. That
since actually,
which is by the way a particularly חידוש chiddush in the case
of if you do an עולה Ola like a חטאת, chatat if
you only do one סימן when you're supposed to be two, you
could say you did the whole act of the מליקה melikah incorrectly,
but nevertheless we don't look at it like a נבלה. neveilah. Okay,
that's the next משנה. Mishna. Okay, so if you say that this
עולה Ola that you did like a חטאת chatat, was only one
סימן, מכדי תני סיפא, midei t'ni seifa, the end, meaning the next
משנה Mishna is going to teach, כולן אין מטמאין בבית הבליעה, kulan
ein metamin be'veit habli'ah, they don't cause טומאה, tumah, they're not treated
like a נבלה. neveilah. We'll get to that, that's not the focus
of this גמרא right now. ומועלין בהן, u'moalin bahen, the focus of
the גמרא is that there is מעילה. me'ilah. Now what does that
mean? It means here you have an עולה, Ola basically there's going
to be מעילה me'ilah because it goes, it gets burnt on the
מזבח. mizbe'ach. Okay, it never becomes accessible to human use. But a
חטאת, chatat there's no מעילה me'ilah if done properly after the blood
is done, because now it becomes accessible to human use, it's אכיל,
achil, edible by the כהנים. Kohanim. Okay, but if you went ahead
here and you did this חטאת chatat incorrectly, so you did a
חטאת chatat, incorrectly, it can't be eaten by the כהנים, Kohanim, מעילה
me'ilah still applies to the חטאת chatat, even after it's been, the
blood has been done. This חטאת, chatat because it's never אכיל, achil,
edible by the כהנים. Kohanim. Okay,
that now, but an עולה Ola, you would think definitely there's מעילה
me'ilah because the עולה Ola, never becomes כשר, Kasher, even when it's
כשר Kasher. there's מעילה, me'ilah, so certainly when it's פסול. passul. But
now we have an interesting opinion coming up in the next משנה.
Mishna. ומועלין בהן. u'moalin bahen. So the גמרא says נימא דלא כרבי
יהושע. neima d'lo k'Rabbi Yehoshua. So are we going to be forced
to say that that next משנה Mishna goes against רבי יהושע? Rabbi
Yehoshua? Why? דרבי יהושע אמר אין מועלין. d'Rabbi Yehoshua amar ein moalin.
Okay, so this is like importing a whole discussion. It would have
been much easier for us to read the משנה Mishna and then
have this discussion, but we'll get there in a minute. But basically
here's what you have to know: The רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון, Rabbi
Elazar b'Rabbi Shimon, that רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua says a bizarre idea.
He says, here's this עולה Ola. that you would think totally it
never gets out of מעילה me'ilah because even done properly it never
gets out of מעילה, me'ilah, certainly done improperly. And he says if
you treat this עולה Ola like a חטאת chatat, in the sense
of that you do the מליקה melikah like a חטאת chatat, and
you do it in the place of a חטאת, chatat, remember I
said before that the point of the משנה Mishna was no matter
how much you try to treat it like the other animal, you
don't, the other קרבן, korban, you don't get to redefine it. רבי
יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua actually says to a certain degree you do get
to redefine it. Not that you make it כשר, but if you
take this עולה, Ola, you do it below, you do it לשם
חטאת, leshem chatat, and you do it like a חטאת, chatat it
is enough like a חטאת chatat that it stops having מעילה me'ilah
apply to it, this bird עולה. Ola It's a very strange idea.
So anyway, what the גמרא's saying is but for him what's critical
is to get it out of מעילה me'ilah is that you, the
way you did the מליקה melikah was you did the מליקה melikah
like a חטאת, Chatat you only did one סימן and not two
סימנים. Simanim So back to where we are. The משנה Mishna says
for us, if you did this עולה Ola. like a חטאת, Chatat
it's invalid. What are we talking about? If we're talking about you
did the מליקה Melika like a חטאת, Chatat. well, according to רבי
יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua what that would lead to is if you did
the מליקה Melika like a חטאת Chatat and you did it לשם
חטאת leshem chatat and you did it below, whatever, that would lead
to a scenario in which there was no מעילה. me'ilah. But the
next משנה Mishna says there is מעילה. me'ilah. So we, that does
not read to say our case is that you did the מליקה
Melika like a חטאת Chatat because then the next משנה Mishna which
says there's no מעילה me'ilah would not be true according to רבי
אלעזר ברבי שמעון. Rabbi Elazar b'Rabbi Shimon. You sort of get that?
Sort of. Okay, so kind of. Okay.
Alright, so alright, see here, you got here, maybe maybe we'll do
a visual. Okay. Visuals always help. Okay, so here you've got this
עולה Ola *olah*, which is supposed to be up there, and you're
doing it down here, okay, this is an your עולה *olah*, okay,
and you're going to go ahead and you're going to do it
like a חטאת Chatat *chatas*, so you're going to do one סימן
*siman*, okay, לשם Leshem חטאת Chatat *leshem chatas*, and you're doing it
in the place of a חטאת Chatat. *chatas*. So in that case,
even though it's an עולה *olah*, and in that case רבי Rabbi
יהושע Yehoshua *Rabbi Yehoshua* says, רבי Rabbi יהושע Yehoshua. *Rabbi Yehoshua* says
there's no מעילה Meila *me'ilah*. Because you did everything like a חטאת
Chatat *chatas*, there's no מעילה Meila *me'ilah*. That's what he's going to
say. Okay, now our משנה Mishna *mishnah* basically says, okay, our משנה
*mishnah* sort of says like this, it says חטאת Chatat *chatas* that
you did like an עולה *olah* like an עולה *olah* is פסול
Pasul, *pasul*. Then it says עולה *olah* that you're going to do
like a חטאת Chatat, *chatas*, okay, is also going to be פסול
*pasul*. That's the basic structure of our משנה *mishnah*, right? Okay. And
then the next משנה *mishnah* says, oh, but by the way, there
is מעילה Meila *me'ilah* in those two cases. Okay. So here's what
the גמרא *gemara* says: עולה *olah* doing like a חטאת Chatat *chatas*,
what does it mean doing? If doing like a חטאת Chatat. *chatas*
meant one סימן *siman*, okay, and then it's פסול *pasul*, then to
say then then there would be no מעילה Meila *me'ilah* according to
רבי Rabbi יהושע Yehoshua *Rabbi Yehoshua*. So the next line that says
there is מעילה Meila. *me'ilah* would be not like רבי Rabbi יהושע
*Rabbi Yehoshua*. And we'd rather it be according to everyone. So we
don't want to read that this means that the מליקה Melika *melikah*
was like a חטאת Chatat. *chatas*, because then the next line that
there's מעילה Meila. *me'ilah* would not be true according to רבי Rabbi
יהושע *Rabbi Yehoshua*. Right, and the next משנה *mishnah* is ליבא דכולא
*liba d'kula*. And we want the next משנה *mishnah* to be according
well, yeah, also because the משנה *mishnah* introduces something and then afterwards
introduces the debate of רבי יהושע *Rabbi Yehoshua* and רבי אליעזר Eliezer
*Rabbi Eliezer*. That's correct too. Okay, so the גמרא *gemara* says like
this: So נימא דלא כרבי יהושע *neima d'lo keRabbi Yehoshua*? דאי כרבי
יהושע אמר Amar אין Ein מועלין Mo'alin *de'ee keRabbi Yehoshua amar ein
moalin*. So fine. So what we'd rather say here is we don't
want this case to be talking about the scenario that's debated about
מעילה Meila. *me'ilah*. So this case, when you did it like a
חטאת Chatat, *chatas*, does not mean one סימן *siman*. When it says
you did it like a
חטאת Chatat *chatas*... excuse me, this case that it says you did
it like a חטאת Chatat, *chatas* is talking about not the one
סימן *siman* like a חטאת Chatat *chatas*, but what you did with
the blood. Okay? The עולה *olah* blood you're supposed to squeeze out,
and the חטאת Chatat *chatas* blood you're supposed to squirt, and here
when you you squirted it rather than squeezing it out, and that's
what invalidated it, okay? Now again, the question is: Did you do
both? Because here you're supposed to squirt and squeeze out. Okay, so
if what it means is you only squirted and you didn't squeeze
out, okay, then you understand why it's invalid. You didn't do what
the Torah says. The Torah says ונמצה *venimtza*. So you just didn't
do the right thing. It's not because you did it like a
חטאת Chatat *chatas*, it's because you didn't do what you needed to
do. But if you squirted and squeezed out, right, then again that's
the question: So what's the basis of saying it's פסול *pasul*? Just
because it's like the other thing? The גמרא *gemara* does not explore
that. Yes. I think the previous example should have to do with
the עבודה *avodah*, למעלה *lemalah*, למטה Lemata *lematah*.
Which? This case? Yes, this case is למעלה *lemalah*. But the רבי
יהושע *Rabbi Yehoshua* when you do an עולה לשם Leshem חטאת Chatat
*olah leshem chatas*, you're also doing it in the place of the
חטאת Chatat *chatas*. The גמרא *gemara* was asking about מליקה *melikah*.
It would have to be the רישא Reisha *reisha* of of the
עולה *olah* cases. Because...
yes, yes, the case here included both cases, but then it went
on to do
with... yes, but yes, the but this case of the רבי יהושע
*Rabbi Yehoshua* is that you're doing it below. But you're right, the
גמרא *gemara* is starting in this case of an עולה כמעשה Kema'aseh
חטאת Chatat? *olah kema'aseh chatas* above, but it includes later in the
משנה *mishnah* also the case below. Okay. So the גמרא *gemara* says
like this: אלא אימא Eima במצוי *ela eima bemitzui*.
So, okay,
the point was the problem with this עולה *olah* was that you
did the that you did rather than do the squeezing, you did
the squirting. That was the problem. אימא סיפא Seifa *eima seifa*, let's
look at the end. עולה שעשאה She'asah למטה Lemata כמעשה Kema'aseh חטאת
Chatat, לשם Leshem חטאת *olah she'asa'ah lematah kema'aseh chatas leshem chatas*. So
now this is the our משנה *mishnah* coming up, not the משנה
*mishnah* we read. Okay, so that's this case. You did it on
the bottom, like a חטאת *chatas* לשם Leshem חטאת *leshem chatas*. And
like a חטאת *chatas* here means one סימן *siman*. Okay. רבי אליעזר
Eliezer אומר Omer מועלין Mo'alin בה Bah. *Rabbi Eliezer omer moalin bah*,
רבי יהושע אומר Omer אין Ein מועלין Mo'alin בה Bah. *Rabbi Yehoshua
omer ein moalin bah*, that there's no מעילה Meila *me'ilah*. So דשני
במאי *deshani bemai*? אלימא במצוי *alima bemitzui*? So if you say that
the case there where the מעילה Meila *me'ilah* debate is the squeezing
case, אימא דאמר רבי יהושע דשני במליקה, BiMelika במצוי מי אמר? Amar
*eima d'amar Rabbi Yehoshua deshani bemelikah, bemitzui mi amar?* We understand רבי
יהושע *Rabbi Yehoshua* to say... it's not saying here why we understand
him to say that, but we understand the רבי יהושע *Rabbi Yehoshua*
case to be the issue of מליקה *melikah*, that that's what allows
it to be redefined. אלא במליקה *ela bemelikah*, it must be מליקה
*melikah*. So now in order to allow this statement of מעילה Meila.
*me'ilah* to be דברי הכל *divrei hakol*, to not be part of
this debate, we said that this is talking about מצוי *mitzui*, right?
Okay. And this debate here is talking about מליקה *melikah*. So now
the גמרא *gemara*'s got a problem. First we talk we said the
first part here, right, was talking about מליקה *melikah*... at least according
to one read. Now we're back to, now this case is מיצוי,
and now the case back here is going, we keep on switching,
right, what is the scenario of what's being changed? So the גמרא
says אימא סיפא ואלא Ve’ela במליקה רישא Reisha וסיפא VeSeifa מליקה מציעה
Metzi'a במיצוי? BiMeitzoi? אין, רישא וסיפא VeSeifa מליקה מציעה Metzi'a במיצוי, BiMeitzoi,
get used to it. Okay,
so it's all based on context. Okay, so anyway, so one more
time, what do we have? We have the following. חטאת done like
an עולה is invalid. What does it mean done like an עולה?
It could mean that you severed both סימנים. Simanim Then why would
it be invalid? You just did extra. Right. So it could be
it's invalid because you violated the verse, although the גמרא never says
that. It could be it's invalid somehow there's just an idea that
if you do it like the other קרבן Korban it invalidates, but
that doesn't really explain why we know that. Okay, so that's one
scenario: you severed both סימנים. The other scenario, which is easier, is
that what does it mean that you did it like an עולה?
It means that you just squeezed the blood and you didn't squirt
it. And that, therefore, what would invalidate that would be that you
didn't do the blood correctly. That's, that's that case. An עולה that
you did for a חטאת is invalid. What could that mean? That
could mean that you only severed one סימן. Then it's invalid simply
because you didn't sever both סימנים and the תורה Torah tells you
you have to sever both סימנים. Or it could mean that you
that you did that you squirted the blood. Now, if you squirted
and squeezed the blood, not clear why it should be invalid. But
if you only squirted and you were supposed to squeeze, then that
would be a better explanation. Okay, so basically pretty, some of those
variations are clear why they're invalid because you didn't do what you
needed to do. Others, it's the suggestion is that what invalidates is
that it's like the other thing, the very just the fact that
it's like the other thing invalidates, that's less clear why that's a
source of invalidating. Now we get on to the משנה which is
that we were referring to before, which would have been easier had
we read it earlier. Okay. וכולן Vechulan אין מטמאין Metame'in בבית Bebeit
הבליעה. Habli'ah.
Even though these are invalid, you don't treat it like נבלה. Neveila.
And as I said, that's particularly a חידוש Chidush if the עולה
you only did one סימן. Even though you didn't do the מליקה
fully, okay, we don't treat it like a נבלה. Neveila. Okay, because
I guess you still did a מליקה that would have counted by
a חטאת. Okay. ומועלין Umo'alin בהן, Bahen, and there is מעילה Meila
because the only thing there wouldn't have been מעילה Meila. is had
you done the חטאת correctly. Then the חטאת would have become edible
by the כהנים. Kohanim. Since you didn't do the חטאת correctly, nothing
ever becomes edible for כהנים Kohanim and therefore מעילה Meila. remains. חוץ
Chutz מחטאת Mechatat העוף Ha'of שעשאה She'asah למטה כמעשה חטאת לשם Leshem
חטאת.
The only thing that wouldn't be מעילה Meila. is if you do
the חטאת correctly, if you do the חטאת where it should be
done, לשם Leshem חטאת, and then it can be eaten by the
כהנים, Kohanim, then there stops being מעילה. Meila Okay. Now עולת Olat
העוף שעשאה למטה כמעשה חטאת לשם Leshem חטאת. And here's what we
now just referred to before: you did the עולה, but everything you
did made it look like a חטאת. You did it below, you
did it לשם Leshem חטאת, you did the סימנים and the blood
like a חטאת—or the סימנים in particular, the גמרא said—okay, in that
case רבי אליעזר אומר מועלין Mo'alin בה. Bah I'm sorry, it's still
not כשר, therefore there's, it's an עולה and it's still not כשר.
רבי יהושע אומר אין מועלין בה. Bah, Nope, because everything was like
a חטאת, that enough puts it in the חטאת category, even though
this is not edible by anyone, okay, to say that there's no
מעילה. Meila Very strange idea. So רבי אליעזר challenges, אמר Amar רבי
אליעזר ומה Umah אם Im חטאת שאין She'ein מועלין בה Bah לשמה.
Lishma. The חטאת itself, if you do it correctly there's no מעילה.
That's the one thing that there really is no מעילה if you
do it correctly. כששינה Kesheshina שמה Shemah מועלין בה, Bah? if you
do it incorrectly and invalidate, you certainly derail it and the מעילה
remains because it never becomes permissible. So the one thing that could
become permissible when it gets פסול, even in that case there's מעילה.
עולה שמועלין Shemo'alin בה לשמה, Lishma, עולה which even when it's done
correctly there's מעילה because it all goes to the מזבח. Mizbe'ach. כששינה
Kesheshina שמה Shemah אינו Eino דין Din שימעלו Sheyim'alu בה? When you
change it in the wrong way and you more invalidate it, I
mean you invalidate it, you know, how should it be? Of course
there should be מעילה. Yeah.
Which is exactly what the answer is. Which is what the answer
is. אמר לו Lo רבי יהושע. But still, where does he get
the idea that it allows it to recategorize it? אמר לו Lo
רבי יהושע לא, no, I don't buy that question. אם Im אמרת
Amarta בחטאת Bechatat ששינה Sheshina שמה Shemah לשם עולה, by a חטאת
if you did it לשם עולה, שכן Sheken שינה Sheshina שמה Shemah
לדבר Ledavar שיש Sheyesh בו Bo מעילה. There, the way you tried
to recategorize it was as an עולה. Well, an עולה there is
מעילה. So I believe when you do the whole, it's like entirely
like the other thing, that allows it in some virtual way to
be as if it gets recategorized.
So okay, a חטאת done לשם עולה, you're not, it's going to
be מעילה because even if you recategorized it, you recategorized it like
an עולה and there's מעילה by an עולה. תאמר Tomar בעולה Ba'ola
ששינה Sheshina שמה Shemah לשם חטאת? But if an עולה you did
it like a חטאת, there you recategorized it to something that... Doesn't
have מעילה *meilah*, שכן שינוי שמו לדבר שאין בו מעילה *sheken shinui
shemo l'davar she'ein bo meilah*. Okay, so the point is that's all
very nice, but where do you get the idea that you can
recategorize it? And if he said somehow and it's actually כשר *kosher*
as a חטאת *Chatas* and the כהנים *kohanim* can eat it, okay,
we'd still want to know where, but at least it would be
here you're coming up with this thing that somehow it gets to
be recategorized to this degree for the purpose of מעילה *meilah* that
we view it as if it were a חטאת *Chatas*. Okay, אמר
ליה *amar leih* Rabbi Eliezer, so Rabbi Eliezer says come on, I'm
going to do a reductio ad absurdum, you know, really, you get
to recategorize things like this, let me give you this scenario. והרי
קדשי קדשים *V'harei kodshei kodashim*, you have a קדשי קדשים *kodshei kodashim*,
an עולה *olah*, an אשם *asham*, a חטאת *Chatas*, they're supposed to
be שחט'ד *shechted* in the north. So you go ahead and like
in your scenario you do everything the way of the other קרבן
*korban*, rather you're going to treat it like a קדשים קלים *kodashim
kalim*, שחטן בדרום *shachatan badarom*, you do it in the south. ושחטן
לשם קדשים קלים *V'shachatan l'shem kodashim kalim*, and you שחט *shecht* it
with the כוונה *kavanah* that it should be a שלמים *shelamim*. Now,
according to you, that should recategorize it and now we should say
that there should be like no מעילה *meilah* because there's no מעילה
*meilah* by a שלמים *shelamim*. יוכיחו שכן שינוי שמו לדבר שאין בו
מעילה *Yochichu sheken shinui shemo l'davar she'ein bo meilah*, that recategorizes it
to something that there's no מעילה *meilah*, ומועלין בה *u'moleh bah*, and
even you can see that in that case since you made this
a פסול *pasul* עולה *olah*, פסול *pasul* חטאת *Chatas*, a פסול *pasul*
אשם *asham*, whatever you did, there's מעילה *meilah*. It never becomes permissible
to be eaten. You don't have this idea that it gets to
recategorize it and treat it as if it's a שלמים *shelamim* and
there's no מעילה *meilah*. So if you can see the case of
the שלמים *shelamim*, you don't get to recategorize, you know, an עולה
*olah* like a שלמים *shelamim*. אף על פי ששינה שמה לדבר שאין
בו מעילה שמועלין בה *Af al pi she-shinnah shemah l'davar she'ein bo
meilah she-meilah bo*. So the same by a bird עולה *olah*, how
do you get to recategorize it as a חטאת *Chatas*? Why does
this work by birds and it doesn't work by animals? Nobody says
you get to recategorize the larger animals. אמר ליה *amar leih* Rabbi
Yehoshua, Rabbi Yehoshua said back to him, לא *lo*, no, I don't
accept that challenge. אם אמרת בקדשי קדשים ששחטן בדרום ושחטן לשם קדשים
קלים *Im amarta b'kodshei kodashim she-shachatan badarom v'shachatan l'shem kodashim kalim*, your
scenario of like I don't know the אשם *asham* that you שחט'ד
*shechted* as a שלמים *shelamim*, שכן שינוי שמו לדבר שיש בו איסור
והיתר *sheken shinui shemo l'davar she-yesh bo issur v'heter*,
fundamentally I would say it by the cow and the sheep. The
only point is is that a שלמים *shelamim* is not totally excluded
from מעילה *meilah*. Because even a שלמים *shelamim*, the entrails, there is
מעילה *meilah* that gets burnt on the altar. The only thing that
there's not מעילה *meilah* by the שלמים *shelamim* is the meat. So
therefore if you're trying to, you know where they say, one man's
reductio ad absurdum is another man's אין הכי נמי *ein hachi nami*,
you know. So so you're trying to say it's crazy, you know
what, if it were true that a שלמים *shelamim* there would be
no מעילה *meilah* by by the entire שלמים *shelamim*, I would have
said that that was true, an אשם *asham* that you treated like
a שלמים *shelamim* it would go out even though it would become
פסול *pasul* or whatever it would be, an עולה *olah*, whatever, it
would go out of מעילה *meilah* because you had recategorized it to
something that there's no מעילה *meilah*. The only problem is is that
even with a שלמים *shelamim* there's מעילה *meilah* for part of it.
And therefore this recategorization doesn't help. Okay and that's why it doesn't
help by the שלמים *shelamim*. אבל תאמר בעולה ששינה שמה לדבר שכולו
היתר *Aval tomar b'olah she-shinnah shemah l'davar she-kulo heter*. Okay, by a
חטאת *Chatas*, a bird חטאת *Chatas*, you eat the whole thing as
the משנה *Mishnah* says אין למזבח בו כלום *ein l'mizbe'ach bo klum*.
After the bird, the whole after the blood, the whole bird is
eaten by the כהנים *kohanim* by the כהנים *kohanim*. So yes, I've
got this idea that when you completely treat it like an other
thing and that other thing is completely excluded from מעילה *meilah*, the
only example of something completely excluded from מעילה *meilah* is a bird
חטאת *Chatas*, okay, that that is enough to take it out of
the category of מעילה *meilah*. It doesn't make it כשר *kosher*, but
it's enough to take it out of the category of מעילה *meilah*.
So we'll continue tomorrow with this issue of this debate around מעילה
*meilah*.